I had a question. I'm not sure if it's really\h
suited to the format of a group discussion,
because it's to some degree personal.
But it's about\hdealing with doubt, especially in the
initial stages of the training. I personally have\h
always been a very avoidant person, so my main
way of dealing with problems was to
not\hdeal with them for the most part.
And I am some degree afraid of whether my interest in\h
the dhamma is some kind of elaborate strategy to
avoid the stresses of what would be called
"the\hnormal life". And besides that, another
source of doubt are the - you probably heard that\h
that question many times -  the supernatural
aspects of the dhamma or some inconsistencies\h
in the suttas, or for example - I don't know -\h\h
"Are the immaterial attainments the same thing\h
as jhānas? Are they really part of the training?"\h\h
and so on, those kinds of things. That really
sometimes shakes my faith in what I'm trying to do.
So do you have any advice for that kind\h
of situation or any practical contemplations that
would be helpful in dealing with those matters?
In terms of the practice being a strategy for avoiding things,
the question\his: Why would you not want to avoid suffering?
Why would you be worried about\h
the dhamma being a strategy for avoidance?
It's because you know deep down that avoidance results\h
in suffering. Avoidance results in not dealing
with things which then makes the problem fester,\h
which then makes you suffer even more. So whatever
you do, whether it's avoidance or non-avoidance,\h
it's going to be because you think that it will
free you from suffering. So because that is the\h
fundamental goal of the dhamma,
you cannot go wrong by practicing the dhamma.\h
Now of course, like you said it's a the problem is
mainly that pressure of doubt; it's not whether\h
it makes sense or not. The doubt will make
you question whether it makes sense or not. Even\h
though if you sit down and think about it, it does
make sense. So what you have to recognize\h
is that doubt is a symptom of a untrained mind.
So you will not be able to clear the doubts before\h
you start the training, because it's precisely the
the result of the training is the overcoming of\h
doubt. So if you keep that context, like:\h
"Okay, whatever I do I'll be doing it because I want\h
to avoid suffering", then you will not be able to
ignore that all these other ways that you might\h
go about it, that are not the dhamma, are actually
making the problem worse. So you would just
need\hto keep bringing to mind that context
and reminding yourself that even those things\h
you mentioned, the immaterial attainments and the
jhānas, none of that fundamentally affects the core\h
principle of: "If I act out of craving, I'm making my
suffering worse", which is all that the dhamma is.
All these immaterial attainments: you don't\h\h
even necessarily have to go through those in order\h
to free yourself from suffering. So that has to be
the underlying context that is\huniversal,
and it's something that people
recognize even outside of the Buddhist teaching to\h
a minimal degree; that if you act out of desires,
act out of aversion, you know, break precepts\h
and live an unwholesome lifestyle,
you will suffer more. And really hammering down\h
that recognition is more than enough for you to
practice the fundamental aspects of the training.\h
And the other thing you mentioned was about the...
What was the second question? The essence
of it\his that the parts of the dhamma or the
content of the suttas that seems uncertain or hard\h
to believe. It also in some way casts doubt on
what, you know, I agree is the essence of the dhamma,\h
the freedom from suffering, restraint, and so on.
Well, yes, that's the thing. So it\h
it shouldn't cast out on it because
inevitably, when you read those things like\h
immaterial attainments and all this stuff,\h\h
you will be reading it through assumptions of...\h
you haven't ever ventured near the ocean\h
and yet you're reading this detailed book about
the ocean\hfloor and the fish and all these things
that would be completely abstract for you and\h
then you might wonder: "Oh well, it doesn't\h\h
really make sense that you would have\h
this huge heights and stuff that
go all the way down to, you know, lower than anybody\h
has ever observed." That sounds outrageous\h\h
and that's precisely because there\h
is no concrete basis for it to connect with it.
But if you put that stuff aside, because again,\h
all suttas are extreme amounts of volume of
information that nobody would have had
access\hto in the Buddha's time,
and the Buddha wouldn't have started talking about these\h
immaterial attainment to somebody who had no basis\h\h
to even understand what he was talking about.\h
So it's only because now we have access to all
these suttas that then all this information
starts creating doubts and all these things.
But it's a gradual training. The way that\h
it actually unfolds is a gradual training where
you focus on what's relevant for you at the time,\h
because that is the basis\h\h
where you will be able to see the direct challenge\h
and how it will help you overcome suffering.
So most basically it would be the precepts. Almost\h
anybody who has a degree of self transparency
will be able to see that on days where they've\h
been breaking precepts, they will have a more
wild and uncontrollable mind than on days\h
where they don't. And I don't
need to be speculating, like: "Oh is this really\h
what the Buddha meant?" or something. You can
very directly see the benefit of doing that for\h
yourself and then when you have accomplished that
then you move on to the next stage and to the next\h
stage and at a certain point then you would come
to these immaterial attainments and then you would\h
see how you practice that, and with the same degree
of clarity that you can now see how you would\h
practice the precepts. But yes, again,
none of this kind of rational laying out of
considerations is going to undo that pressure,
that emotional pressure of doubt that you feel.\h
So, that's something that you have to
keep in mind because otherwise it would keep\h
baiting you into trying to resolve it, whereas
the very way that you deal with it, is by not\h
acting out of it. You need have faith. Yes.\h
And you also have to recognize all the other things\h
that you do. If you still act out,
chase after sense pleasures, act out of ill will,\h
distract yourself, basically break the eight
precepts, that same intensity of pressure or
intensity of wildness is feeding into the doubt.
So you will have doubt for as long as you act\h
out of sensuality, basically. If you
were to, let's say, not change your lifestyle but\h
put all the effort into clarifying everything
about the suttas and get a PhD in the\h
entire Pali canon, the pressure of the
doubt would remain completely unchanged,\h
because that's not where it comes from.
I have a follow-up question. You said\h
overcome doubt. Did you mean that doubt
never arises again or did you mean that even\h
if it arises, you're not touched by it?
Well, let's say you have to differentiate between\h
not knowing something and then feeling doubt.
Doubt is an emotional\hstate
that is always bound with craving.
So doubt is when you don't know the answer and\h
you have a resistance to not knowing the answer.
You have an emotional pressure that makes you want\h
to find the answer. So in that sense, yes; doubt
would never arise if you tame your mind. But that\h
doesn't mean that you would know everything.\h
There will be countless things that you don't know.\h
But the difference is you will not feel pain,
pressure, discomfort on account of not\h
knowing those things. And that's really
all that the problem was. It wasn't\h
the lack of knowledge, it was the suffering.
Sometimes you could see that in
very practical scenarios, like you can\h\h
have spent spent days trying to figure out\h
the answer to some question or get some piece
of information that you didn't have before,\h
and then for what whatever reason you get
distracted, something else in your life happens, \h
you forget about the question and then you try
to think about it again and you don't really\h
care about the answer anymore. So then that
shows you that it wasn't actually the lack\h
of the answer that was making you suffer.
So you're saying doubt is lack of knowledge\h
affected by creating. Yes.
Is there a direction to this\hclarification?
Because trying to resolve doubt
and just sort of coming after\h
it, taking it for granted and just go out
out absorbing yourself into it,
but it seems that\hthere's another direction
that is beyond doubt. Yes.
But it won't necessarily feel like it.
No, but it is that internal direction which is\hwhere you resolve doubts, because everything\h\h
external you can be - if you attend to it
wrongly\h- in doubt about.
It just feels like that direction is a\h
thread that a puthujjana could follow and
even in admitting and coming to terms\h
with: 'I know that I suffer', it's like
I don't know the way out; I know\h
that I'm lost, and knowing that I'm lost
I'm less lost. Yes. And that's a kind of a step.
So I suffer but\hat least
having that perspective then allows\h
me to maybe search\h\h
If you were to truly accurately\h
understand "I am suffering", that would already be
like as satipatthāna sutta describes: "knowing dukkha as dukkha,\hyou abide independent, not clinging to anything
in the world", which is already the right view.
So it's\hnot even that you would need a separate step.
If you pursue that direction sufficiently\h
to see an arisen feeling of suffering on the
right level, that would already undo the\hproblem,
because the problem is ignorance, as the suttas say.
You're feeling the suffering, but you're not\h
aware of the extent of it.
So that's the reason why the suttas would say that\h
the precursor to the right view is yoniso manasikāra.
So it's not the right view yet; it is something that a\h
puthujjana would be able to practice,
and if cultivated long enough - which happens through, again,\h
the precepts and sense restraint - they would be able
to get it to the strength, let's say,
where it's potent enough to properly
see an arisen feeling as an arisen feeling.
A question on that is: "Is yoniso manasikāra...
so a puthujjana can be developing it..."
Actually, that that brings\h
me back to something I wanted to say.\h\h
So yes, that direction of yoniso manasikāra, which\h
is the direction beyond doubt if you want to call it that:
anybody has access to that,
but knowing that that is the direction
beyond doubt, that's what the right view\his.
So that's why it's knowing that you know,
not just knowing. Anybody\h
can to some extent recognize
that right level, but being sure and unable to\h
doubt that that is the right level and hence to
to go there and sufficiently "hang out" there,\h
long enough in order for that to sink in, and
that no matter what happens - seven rebirths,\h
millions of things that would happen in that
time frame - that they're unable to forget that\h
this is the right level. That's the difference.
So on a practical level, if there is a pressure\h
of say doubt at the time, the direction
of engaging with the craving and the doubt is\h
kind of going into that subject of what the
doubt is and trying to resolve it and thinking and\h
thinking, and so the right direction, that
right internal direction, I guess the direction\hof yoniso
manasikāra would then be to say: "There is a pressure of
doubt right now" and then just staying there.
Is that essentially what it is? Yes.\h\h
Well, that's what you will try to do. But if only it\h
were that simple, obviously. You will try that,
but you will find yourself still to some\hextent...
the common thing that would happen is:
you would start to over clarify: "Okay, so now\h
what exactly do I do, so that I don't engage with
the doubt?" And then now that's what the doubt\h
became established in. So because you can kind
of think about it and it makes sense and:
"Okay, yes, that's what I'm going to do now",
but when it actually comes up and then there's\h
that whole momentum associated with it, you won't
be able to maintain the same level of clear
perspective that you have when the pressure isn't there.
So that's the tricky part; almost anything,
including your remembering of the practice,
will end up infected with the doubt,\h
will become your way of acting out of the doubt.\h\h
So then that's why it won't be perfect from the\h
beginning, but if you keep doing it, you keep doing it,
eventually these ways in which...
your recognition of the problem, of where the
acting out begins, starts to get more\h
and more refined. So then you wouldn't be able to
overlook what you would have overlooked before,\h
which is that even this attempt to clarify what
the right endurance is and what the yoniso manasikāra is,\h
that too is falling within the doubt.
And then your attempt to stay\h
with that internal dimension would more and
more accurately end up in being actually that, and not\h
some other distraction.
That's why seeing the signs of the mind is the\hnecessary prerequisite for everything to work,\h\h
because if you're not seeing the signs of the mind,\h
you won't be aware of that kind of "under the radar"\h\h
sort of background momentum that's pushing you\h
to do something that you think is wholesome,
in this case clarifying what is the right endurance\h
and not acting out of the doubt and so on.
It's like a perpetually dynamic thing.\h
So that's why it's kind of like...
maybe one example would be: you have to\h
look at the stock market prices, but then you
only look at the prices right now, and\h
for the rest of your life you make decisions based
on those initial prices that you saw.
Whereas\hyou will only be able to make the right
decisions if constantly you know the current\h
price, which is the current state of the mind.
And essentially then when you get to the point\h
where you endure those things without acting
out of them in any way, then you will\h
not suffer. Then basically that's what\h\h
the absence of craving is; being able to not move\h
whatsoever, not needing to do anything about it.
But is it possible that the pressure\h
doesn't arise in the first place?\h
Yes. So that's when you see the\h
feeling. Exactly.
If the feeling is understood for what it is,\h
if there is no momentum to act out of it,
then there is no pressure. So the pressure\h
is there to the extent that there is craving.